I pray that with this day of beginnings, with a baptism,
that you will help us to know which direction to take our first steps
to bringing everything to you. In Jesus' name, amen.
Well, good morning.
Good morning.
So glad to see everyone this morning. If you haven't met me yet, my name is Ryan.
I have the privilege of being one of the pastors here.
I'm super excited for this day as we celebrate baptisms.
Baptism is a huge deal for us around here.
We get excited. We get to celebrate people making a decision to follow after Jesus with their lives.
And today's been a bit of a celebratory day,
but I also know that some of you might come into the room this morning with heartache, grief, pain, suffering.
And I thought that song that we just sang was a perfect invitation to remember whether you're here and you're celebrating or whether you're here and you're suffering.
There's a place for you at the table this morning.
I have two quick announcements before we hop into our message.
The first is an update on our parking lot fundraiser.
Some of you might be familiar.
We have planned to redo our entire parking lot,
and then we wanted to raise funds to do the parking lot for the kids club that we also use.
So we're loving our neighbor as ourself, but also we use it as much as they do.
So we thought it was important that we would take that on.
And so I started a fundraiser.
We originally had planned to just do the front of the parking lot of the kids club and leave the side alone.
And we needed to raise $18,000 to do the front of the parking lot.
And our membership asked us to go ahead and get a quote for the side of the parking lot as well.
And I think, I don't have the exact numbers in front of me, I think we ended up having, if we wanted to do both,
we haven't committed to do both, but if we wanted to do both, it was going to be around $25,000, somewhere around that.
You guys have been super generous and have got that campaign started off really well.
And this week I got a text from a friend of mine who was formerly, him and his wife were formerly a pastor of a fresh church.
Some of you used to go to a fresh church.
I know that.
We love a fresh church.
We partnered with them in a lot of ways.
And unfortunately they had to make the decision to close a little bit ago.
And he texted me and he said, hey, you guys were such great partners to us when we were a church and we have some funds left.
And we want to give you $10,000 for your parking lot.
Which is just such a reminder of one of our core values, that we unite for the sake of the gospel,
that the kingdom of God in our city is so much bigger than what happens under our roof.
That there are churches all over our city right now that are meeting with the same purpose that we are meeting for.
And we don't do all the things the same way.
We don't agree on all of the finer points of theology.
But the thing that matters more than anything is that the kingdom of God has come through the death, resurrection of Jesus.
And we get to participate in that kingdom, cultivating that kingdom on earth.
And that doesn't happen alone.
We have to do that together.
And so I'm so thankful for a fresh church, for Sean, for Stephanie.
And for those of you that had previously given to a fresh church, your generosity continues to have an impact in our city.
And so I'm just so thankful for them.
I don't, again, I don't have the exact figures.
I think that pretty much gets us to the point where we're going to be able to do both parking lots.
We're going to finalize it this week so we know exactly where we're at.
But we're pretty much there.
So thank you so much for your generosity.
Yeah, that's great.
And I just love how God works because I'm, first of all, I'm not the type of person that likes to ask people for money.
And then to make it a parking lot, which is like a thing that you have to have, but it's not fun to be like, to pay for a parking lot.
And so I'm just, I love how God always provides for his people.
Secondly, we have Canvas Connection right after service.
It's going to start in the Kids Club from 1145.
It's going to start right at 1145.
It's going to go no longer than 1230, and I have refreshments for you.
So if you are new or newer to Canvas and you just want to learn a little bit more or get connected with other people that are new in a room this big,
you might not know who's new, who's not new.
You might feel isolated or alone.
This is really just a great opportunity for you to come and get to know people, ask questions about our church.
I will be there, and I will do my best to give you the brief synopsis of who we are as a church and allow you to ask questions.
It's going to be two weeks long, this week and next week, and so I'd love to have you join us.
Maybe you've been coming to Canvas for a while, and you want to just see who's new and meet them and welcome them.
Come along.
We've got bagels.
It'll be fun.
Sound good?
All right.
So today, we are continuing a series we started last week called A Summer's Journey Through the Life and Ministry of the Apostle Paul,
who we know as Saul right now.
Barrett and Jason did an awesome job on our stage backdrop to emphasize this journey.
A lot of us will be traveling throughout the summer, and what we're going to learn as we look at Saul's life is Saul was always on the move.
Reaching out to new churches, equipping the churches that he had started, he was always on the move.
So that's why we called it A Summer's Journey.
Last week, we started it.
We said that Saul was a Jewish Pharisee from Tarsus, which was a Roman province northwest of Israel.
Sorry, I had to do the never eat soggy Wheaties in my head.
Northwest of Jerusalem.
He was educated in Jerusalem, so he was a very well-established Jew with a very strict doctrine of how to read and interpret the Old
Testament, but he also had a lot of interaction with Roman people.
He probably worked as a tent maker before in his early life in Tarsus, and so he was constantly interacting with Roman people,
listening to their philosophy, their religion.
And so he had this really well-rounded idea of both the Jewish religion and the Roman ideology,
and ultimately that led him to persecute the church.
We looked at last week, he was a part of the first, of actively killing the first Christian martyr named Stephen.
And he really just felt like the early church, the belief in Jesus as the Jewish Messiah was crazy,
and it was his job to make that stop.
So that's where we got to last week.
Let me pray, and then we'll get into our message this week.
Sound good?
Yeah.
Thank you.
I appreciate it.
Oh, Heavenly Father, Abba, we love you so much.
We're so thankful for Jesus.
We're thankful for the kingdom of God.
We're thankful for this family that we have here as our church.
And we just look forward to the opportunity to study your word this morning.
We look forward to the opportunity to celebrate baptisms this morning.
And we just pray that you would be at work in all of our lives,
equipping, encouraging, challenging, convicting.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
Hey, I did forget to say, my message is going to focus somewhat on baptism, especially towards the end.
And so we've got four or five people that have pre-planned, pre-decided to be baptized.
But I am going to do my best to preach the importance of baptism.
And if you're in here, you've never made that decision.
You've never decided to follow Jesus through baptism.
The water's going to be open.
We've got clothes.
We've got towels.
And so I want you even now to be thinking, if that's not something you've decided yet,
what is holding you back from making that decision?
And so I'd love to baptize more than the people we're planning on baptizing.
So if you're in here and you're a believer, begin praying for those people right now,
that their hearts might be softened and that God might be drawing them to the waters of baptism this morning,
because there is a place at the table for each and every one of you.
All right.
If you want to turn your Bibles to Acts chapter 9, that's where we're going to end up.
A few weeks ago, Marissa and I got a couple babysitters lined up so that we could do a,
like our first big time away from Rory since he's been born.
And it was fun.
It was good.
We decided to go on a date to D.C.
There was a worship concert in D.C. in the evening we wanted to go to.
And we're like, well, let's just spend the day in D.C.
We'll go to the Bible Museum.
We'll do some fun things.
It'll be great.
And we quickly learned a lesson that we probably should have learned about 10 years ago.
We've been married for about 10 years.
And that lesson is that we are not as adventurous as we thought we were.
I did all kinds of research and preparation.
I like to plan ahead on these things.
So I pre-reserved a parking spot.
I did all the research, all the street view maps.
I knew where we were going.
I knew where we needed to be.
And about 0.2 seconds into the city, I realized that I had no clue where I was going or what
I was supposed to do.
And the way the GPS told me to go was different from, you know how this works, right?
And so throughout the day in the city, I just experienced three of my least favorite experiences
on planet Earth.
Number one, thinking that you know where you're going, only to realize that you are going in
the opposite direction of where you need to be going.
Number two, realizing you're lost, having no clue where you are.
What a terrible feeling, especially in a city far away that moves much faster than I, West
Virginia boy, like to move.
The pace of my life is just different than the pace of DC life.
Thank you.
Yeah.
And then lastly, like as you realize that you don't know where you're at, looking around
at all of the people from the city and realizing that none of them want to stop their pace
of life to help you figure out where you need to go.
Like, isn't this, isn't this our experience in the city?
There's, there's really a couple of categories of people in the city.
There's people who know exactly where they're going and you are in their way.
There's people, tourists usually like me, who are confident that they think they know where
they're going.
And in reality, they don't.
And then there are deer in headlight, lost people who know that they have no shot of getting
anyone in the city to stop and help them.
Does that make sense?
So these are physical experiences that we have in our lives and it's tense and it's frustrating
and it's confusing and it's difficult.
But I think if we're honest with ourselves, I think if we stop and think about it for a
little bit, we, we also, we also often have these experiences spiritually.
There are times that we think we know where we're going.
We think we're headed in the right direction.
We think we're a good person that us and God are in a good place only to find out later
that maybe we were headed in a direction that God never asked us to go.
Oftentimes it takes us a while to realize that we're headed in the wrong direction.
And sometimes if you're in here and you're honest with yourself, spiritually speaking,
maybe you realize you're lost.
You realize you don't know where to go, but you're looking around for help and you don't
really see anybody that, that, that really actually wants to help you.
Maybe you've reached out a couple of times and the good Christian has said the right thing,
but they haven't actually stopped to guide you along the right path.
And so as we, as we think about these experiences, I think we're going to see all of these experiences
in our story in Acts chapter nine.
And I just want to think about the direction of your life this morning.
Does the direction of your life align with God's intended plan for your life?
And if not, who in here, who might be able to help you kind of along the way?
So Acts chapter nine is where we're going to pick up.
It's after Stephen's stoning, Saul launched a targeted attack on the early church in Jerusalem.
Remember his goal was to, to squash the growth of the church in Jerusalem.
And, um, Saul was pretty active in persecution and he was pretty successful at persecuting the
church.
Um, the problem is how you define success, right?
Like he was pretty aggressive at persecuting the early church, but he didn't accomplish what
he had intended to.
See, he, he intended to accomplish crushing the church, stopping the movement, getting everybody
to give up on Jesus.
But instead what he did is he pushed out these faithful believers.
He persecuted them outside of Jerusalem and they went into Samaria, into Judea, into the
surrounding areas.
And the church began to spread and the church began to grow more and more.
So the thing that Saul wanted to do, Saul wanted to stop the early church from growing.
He persecuted them.
And that persecution actually led to growth and expansion.
Isn't that like God?
Nothing can stop the kingdom of God's growth.
The kingdom of God is the only thing on earth that is eternal.
And no matter how hard anyone tries to stop it, look throughout history, the amount of people
that have tried to stop the movement of Christianity and persecution only grows the church.
So Saul, desperate to accomplish his purposes, decides that if the church has gone out of
the city, then he is going to go out of the city.
He picks a city called Damascus.
He targets the city, I think on purpose because Damascus, um, it's a large, it's a city with
a large Jewish population.
And it seems like from history that it had limited Roman oversight.
And so he picked this city where he thinks there's going to be a lot of Christians and not a
lot of accountability or authority.
And he's going to go there and begin or continue his persecution of the church.
Acts chapter nine, verse one, but Saul still breathing threats and murder against the disciples
of the Lord.
He went to the high priest and he asked them for letters to the synagogues at Damascus so
that if he found anyone belonging to the way men or women, he might bring them bound to Jerusalem.
So Saul has decided that he is going to expand his persecution of the church.
And he's asking the high priest in Jerusalem to give him permission to go to the synagogues
in Damascus so that he can continue his persecution.
And the first thing that I want to point out in our passage today is the title of the people
that Saul is persecuting.
Look with me in verse two, it says, uh, he's asking for letters to the synagogues at Damascus
so that if he found anyone belonging to who?
The way men or women, he might bound them in Jerusalem.
This is what I want to focus on first.
The title of the early church, the title of the early Christians was the way we weren't,
we weren't called Christians at first.
We were called followers of the way.
The term Christian came later.
And what I think is so important about this is that the early Christians, they identified
themselves by the direction of their life.
Their identity wasn't rooted in an intellectual belief or a one-time profession of faith or earthly
political affiliation.
Rather, their identity was rooted in the direction of their lives.
Saul doesn't care if a Jew intellectually agrees with Jesus being the Messiah.
He cares if they are following the way of Jesus.
So I think this is important for us to think about as American Christians because Christianity
in America has become a general category for people that don't necessarily identify as people
actively seeking to follow Jesus.
Is that a fair assessment?
It's a general terminology.
The category has become so broad that it includes a large number of people who don't actually
desire to follow Jesus or obey him at all.
They might intellectually agree with some of the truths in the Bible.
They might align politically with a group of people who call themselves Christian and vote a certain
way.
They might have grown up going to church every once in a while.
But at the end of the day, does their life, is our life, is your life identified by the direction
of your life or just some one-time profession of faith that you made, intellectual agreement that
you have with some ideas in the Bible?
Barna did a survey recently.
It's a really well-known Christian survey.
And they found that 100—listen to this, this is crazy—176 million Americans.
We're like 330-some million, so that's pretty close.
Like, that's a lot—176 million Americans self-identified as Christian, while only 15 million, throughout
the answers to their surveys, demonstrated an intentional pursuit in following and obeying
the teachings of Jesus.
That's 8.5% of all self-identified Christians in America exhibit any pursuit of obedience to
Christianity has become a term that we use for ourselves and for others, but does it mean
what it meant to the early Christians?
If you're in here, you consider yourself a Christian, you would label yourself that way.
Does your life demonstrate an intentional desire to follow and obey the teachings and examples
of Jesus?
There was no other version of Christianity that existed in the first century.
It was, we are followers of the way.
And they got persecuted for it, and they got pushed out of their city, and they continued
to follow the way because they believed the words that Jesus said.
He said, I am the way, the truth, and the life.
No one comes to the Father except through me.
And so if you wanted fellowship with the Father, you did whatever it took, you were okay with
persecution because you were a follower of the way.
So when we think about our Christian identity, I want us to consider, is it the direction
of our life, or is it more about some cultural identity, some political affiliation, or some
intellectual belief, one-time commitment of faith?
Here's a question that I don't know that I'm comfortable asking myself this morning, so we'll
just ask all of you, and then I'll be tense together.
Listen to me, if Saul was persecuting followers of the way in the American church, would he
look at your life and my life and consider us to be a part of that group?
Would he look at our lives?
We come to church on Sundays.
We have a Bible on our shelf.
Maybe we read it.
Maybe we don't.
If someone was persecuting followers of the way in our city, in our church, would he look
at your life?
Would he look at my life?
And would he say, yeah, that's a target of mine?
Let the Holy Spirit do whatever he wants to do with that in you and in me, all right?
So, first thing we want to point out, Saul, is persecuting followers of the way.
Now, there's a really stark contrast.
I love this here.
It's not necessarily in the Greek, but I think the idea is there.
He says, he's on his way to persecuting followers of the way that he might bring them bound to
Jerusalem.
Now, look at this.
Verse 3.
Now he, Saul, went on his way, approaching Damascus, and suddenly a light from heaven shone
around him.
See, I think there's a clear distinction here between followers of the way and Saul going
his way.
There's a very clear contrast here.
Followers of the way and Saul is going his way, and Saul thinks that his way is the way.
Saul thinks that the direction of his life aligns with God's will for his life.
He is confident and convinced that the things that he is doing is the things that he is supposed
to be doing.
And what he's going to realize very quickly is that he's actually headed in the very opposite
direction that God has for him.
And this is a very, very clear picture of how all of humanity interacts with God.
Listen to me.
There are only two spiritual directions that exist in humanity.
Only two.
There is the way, and there is my way.
Your way.
Our way.
There are only two directions, spiritual directions in life.
We are either following the way that God has intended for us, or we are following our own
way.
And that looks different for all of us.
It looks like putting anything but God in the place of God in your life.
But there are only two spiritual directions.
You're either going with the flow that God has laid out for you, which ultimately is obedience
to him, submission to him.
From the very beginning of creation, the fabric of creation was God as a loving father inviting
us humanity, to just follow him, just steward creation in alignment with the way that he called
us to.
From the very beginning, there was rebellion, and that forged the road in the opposite direction.
And from now on, there are only two roads.
There is the way, and there is our way.
Proverbs 14.12 says,
There is a way that appears to be right, but in the end, it leads to death.
And I think so many of us are like Saul.
We're headed in a direction, and we think we're doing right.
We're good people.
We're doing the right things.
We're prioritizing things that matter.
But at the end of the day, if God isn't at the center of our lives, if we haven't submitted
our life to the leadership and lordship of Jesus, we're not heading in the direction that
God intended for us to head.
And that direction ultimately leads to our death and destruction.
Matthew 7.
Enter through the narrow gate, for wide is the gate, and broad is the way that leads to
destruction.
And many will enter through it, but small is the gate, and narrow is the way, the way that
leads to life, and only few will find it.
Jesus was very clear at the end of his very important sermon on the kingdom of God.
There are two spiritual directions.
There is a wide road that many of us follow, and that wide road leads to our destruction.
There's a narrow road that leads to life, and only a few will find it.
So, for you and for me, does the current trajectory of our life line up with God's intended direction?
Are we walking in a way that seems right to us, but ultimately leads to destruction, or are
we walking the narrow road that leads to life?
God's desire for you, ultimately, is that you would submit your life to him as both sovereign
king and creator.
And look, here's the part that I missed for so long growing up in church.
I heard this gospel preached over and over and over again.
I went to a good church with good people, but the thing that I missed, and I don't know if
I missed it because of the way that they communicated or because of the way that I internalized who
I thought God was, but the thing that I missed is that God is not a cosmic tyrant in the sky
that demands your obedience or else.
God is a loving father that knows the consequences of a life lived your own way.
He's the creator, the sustainer, he's a loving father, and he sees us walking down this wide
road that leads to destruction.
And he's not a cosmic tyrant in the sky saying, get it right or get out.
He's a loving father inviting us to realize that we're headed down a path that leads to destruction.
We've got to get this.
If we're going to be genuine followers of Jesus, we have to realize that the invitation
to follow him is an invitation from a loving father who wants us to experience life and
life more abundantly.
His yoke is easy.
His burden is light.
He has come that we might have life and life more abundantly.
But here's the thing, that life, and we're going to see this pictured in baptism, that life
comes on the other side of self-denial and death.
The whole point of the gospel is that life comes on the other side of death.
And so when we baptize people into the water, we're picturing that their old self, their
self that was walking the wide road that leads to destruction, they're voluntarily dying to
that person.
And they are turning around 180 degrees and they are going down the narrow road that leads
to life.
And here's the thing, here's the thing about Saul is I think, I think by this point in
Saul's life, he was having some internal confliction about the direction of his life.
And this is how God works in your life and in my life, right?
There's, as we're going down our road that we think is leading to life, we'll have these
interactions with people.
We'll have these signposts along the way of our life and we'll get these internal like,
hmm, maybe this isn't working the way that I thought it was working.
Maybe I'm not as happy as I thought I was.
Maybe I'm not as confident as I thought I was.
And I think, I think Saul was having these internal challenges in his life.
And there's a couple of reasons I think that, um, the first reason is later in Acts, Saul
recounts his interaction with God on the roads of Damascus.
And we don't get it in Acts chapter nine.
We'll get there in a minute.
But when Saul recounts it, he said that, that Jesus said to him, is it hard for you to kick
against the goads?
There was this, there was this stabbing, this pricking that the Holy Spirit that God was
doing to Saul and Saul knew internally, he was struggling.
He was like, man, I think I'm doing the right thing.
But he was being poked and prodded like an animal who was going in the wrong direction.
And Jesus was trying to say, Saul, you're going in the wrong direction.
You know, the Scriptures, you know, the Old Testament, wake up, you're going the wrong
direction.
Saul was having these internal conflicts.
And yet he kept proudly pushing forward down his way that ultimately would lead to destruction.
The second reason I think that is because he's asking for approval from spiritual leaders
in his life.
This is important because I think we do this all the time.
He's, he's confident.
He's on his way to persecute the church.
But I think there's this internal struggle that he's having.
And so he's going to authorities that he looks up to, spiritual people that have influence
in his life.
And he's saying, I'm doing the right thing, right?
Can you guys affirm me?
Can you give me the documentation that I need so that when anybody asks, so that when I go
to sleep at night, I can say, but they told me it was good.
They told me it was right.
And I think for those of us that are having these internal struggles with God, I think
we do this.
I think we look for people in authority to tell us the thing that we want to do.
We go and search out and we find voices of people that are going to affirm our direction,
whether or not it's God's direction or not.
And I want to caution us that just because a person in authority gives you affirmation
for your lifestyle does not mean that that is on behalf of God.
And so if you are being convicted, challenged by the Holy Spirit, and you're like, you know
what?
This person says it's good.
This group of people affirms my identity or my direction for my life.
Just you do the work.
You pause.
You go back and you see, is this from God or is this from someone else?
I had a really good friend a while back who confessed to me some pretty, pretty bad things
that he was participating in.
And I was super thankful that that confession happened and I gave him what I thought God
would want him to do, how God would want him to respond.
And though he had the bravery, the courage to confess, he didn't like the thing that I told
him I thought God would want him to do.
And he disagreed with me and so I got a couple of his friends that also loved him that cared
about him and I said, we all think that this is the thing that you should do.
And instead he went and he found people that were less in the know with the information and
they affirmed the thing that he wanted to do anyway.
And ultimately those people that were less familiar with the situation, they affirmed him
to do a thing that I think does not honor God.
And I share that story to share with you.
I think we do this when we're convicted, when we're challenged, when we know what God wants
us to do and we don't want to do it rather than humbling ourselves before God and doing
the hard thing, the narrow roadway.
We go and we find people that'll just tell us to keep doing the thing that we want to do.
And those people are affirming us in our direction towards destruction.
So Saul is on his way to do the thing that he thinks is right, looking for affirmation from
other people so that he doesn't have to deal with this conviction that he has from God,
this kicking against the goads.
He hears from God that it's not what he should do and yet he continues to push forward in stubbornness.
Remember we talked about this last week?
He was stubborn, he was self-righteous, he keeps doing the thing he knows he shouldn't
do.
And because God loves Saul and has a plan for Saul, God says, I'm not going to let you go
any further.
Verse four, falling, suddenly a light from heaven shone around him and falling to the ground,
he heard a voice saying to him, Saul, Saul, why are you persecuting me?
Saul said, who are you, Lord?
And the voice replied, I am Jesus whom you are persecuting.
But rise and enter the city and you will be told what you are to do.
The men who were traveling with him stood speechless, hearing the voice but seeing no one.
Saul rose from the ground and although his eyes were open, he saw nothing.
So they led him by the hand and brought him into Damascus and for three days he was without
sight and he neither ate nor drank.
God loves Saul.
God has a plan for Saul and he lovingly confronts Saul in the midst of his rebellion.
I think throughout the path, including Stephen's sermon, God was trying to get a hold of Saul's
attention.
He's trying to say, you're going in the opposite direction.
You're going up, you're going the wrong way.
Wake up, wake up, wake up.
Saul continues to be self-righteous and stubborn.
He keeps finding ways to convince himself that he's doing the right thing, that he is the
hero of the story.
And the whole time God is trying to get his attention.
And finally, God said, enough is enough.
And isn't this similar to a lot of our stories?
Those of us that have been in the waters of baptism.
Haven't we rebelled for a while, felt conviction and kept going?
And for some of us, it takes like a light from heaven, takes God smacking us in the back
of the head and saying, enough is enough.
You're going the wrong way.
I love you too much to let you keep going in the opposite direction that I've called you
to.
So Jesus confronts Saul.
He says, you're going in the wrong way.
He says, why are you persecuting me?
I love this.
Was Saul persecuting Jesus literally, physically?
No, he's persecuting the church.
He's persecuting the followers of Christ.
But I think what's so important for us to learn about this is there's a spiritual reality
at play here that Jesus, he loves his church so much.
He is so ever present with his followers, those of us who follow the way that to persecute
us is ultimately to persecute him.
I think that it's true of the church, but I also think that that's true of all humanity.
I think God created each and every single one of you.
He loves you.
And when you are wronged, when you are sinned against, when you are hurt, I think God kind
of receives that as a sin against himself because he created you and someone sinned against you.
And for God, God sits there with you and he receives the hurt that you received as his
own hurt.
And for those of us who have been deeply wounded by others, I think this should comfort you.
That it was not God's plan that you were hurt, that you were sinned against, that you were
taken advantage of or abused.
That was not God's plan and God does not affirm that.
As a matter of fact, God loves you so much that he views that offense as an offense against
himself.
This is God's response to those of us who are walking our own way.
My belief is God will ultimately confront you.
My belief is God probably is confronting you along the way that he's putting up signs on
your road, down your own way to get your attention.
That this life ultimately, as fun as it might be, as enjoyable as it might be, it will not
lead to your flourishing.
Saul, or God grabs Saul's attention.
He's always lovingly confronting us and providing us with opportunities to repent.
And that language, it's important that we understand that language of repentance.
We've talked about it in the past, so I won't belabor it, but repentance literally just means
to stop and to turn around and go in the opposite direction.
Doesn't that line up with the spiritual ways that we're talking about?
There's really only two ways that we can be walking.
And repentance is we're walking our own way down the wide road that leads to destruction.
And God is trying to get our attention to let us see that there's a ledge there that
we're about to walk off.
Not because he's a cosmic tyrant, but because he's a loving father and he says,
you're about to walk off the side of the cliff, please stop, repent, turn around and go my
way.
Go the way that leads to life and life more abundantly.
This is the invitation of the gospel.
And God is lovingly confronting all of his people.
There's two of my favorite verses that point this out because we don't always see it.
Ecclesiastes 3.11 says that God has placed eternity in your heart.
It means somehow in some spiritual way, you know what you were created for.
You know that you were created for a relationship with the father, the creator of the universe.
You know that there is an order in creation by which you are to participate in this whole
cosmic kingdom.
And when you go in the opposite direction, there is internal conflict.
Not always.
And we numb it and we push it to the side and we get other people to affirm our belief system
so that we can ignore the conviction that's happening.
But ultimately, all of us, I believe God is confronting with the spiritual reality of eternity.
He's trying to get us to understand that we're living for things less than what he has for us.
Second verse is Romans 1, verses 19 and 20.
It says that God has clearly revealed himself to the world through his creative order.
Again, just the way that God created and made things, it's supposed to awaken our eyes to the fact
that he's a loving father.
And oftentimes we put that to the side.
Jesus said to Saul, is it hard for you to kick against the goad?
God was providing signposts along the way for Saul to realize he was going in the wrong direction.
And Saul continually ignored them until finally God made it too obvious for him to ignore.
So I think ultimately all of us, if we walk down the wide road that leads to destruction long enough,
we will have our own Damascus Road experience.
It might not be a light from heaven and Jesus speaking audibly or directly to us,
but oftentimes it is rock bottom.
Like we take this road as far as it will allow us to go, and we hit this rock bottom.
And it's in that rock bottom that God often meets us on the ground, blind, humble, and says,
there's a better way.
There's a better way.
I love what Alan Bandy says.
He says,
to ascend to God, one must often first descend into darkness and defeat.
It often takes us hitting that rock bottom.
It often takes us realizing, being humbled, that our way isn't working the way that we would let others to believe that it is.
And this is where Saul was.
Saul was acting with bravado, with pride, with confidence.
He was trying to let everyone around him know that he was confident, that he was going the way that he was supposed to be going.
But internally, there was a struggle, there was a wrestle, and eventually God brought him to his rock bottom.
To those of you in the room that are still walking that road, I would just invite you, do not wait.
Do not wait until your life hits rock bottom.
Do not wait until the road that you're taking leads you to a dead end.
Today, if you hear the voice of the Lord, do not harden your heart.
So, two spiritual ways.
If you're going the opposite way, God will ultimately confront you.
He probably already has begun that process.
He brings Saul to his knees from a proud man, acting with confidence, to a humble man, blind.
And then he changes the scene.
I love that Luke changes the scene here.
He invites another person into the room.
So, Saul gets to Damascus blind.
He doesn't eat for three days.
Verse 10.
Now, there was a disciple at Damascus named Ananias.
I love the juxtaposition here.
There was Saul walking his way in disobedience, and now waiting for him in Damascus is a follower of the way, listening for obedience.
Now, there was a disciple at Damascus named Ananias, and the Lord said to him in a vision, Ananias.
Ananias responded, here I am, Lord.
And the Lord said to him, rise and go to a street called Straight, and at the house of Judas, look for a man of Tarsus named Saul.
For behold, he is praying.
He has seen a vision of a man named Ananias.
Come in and lay his hands on him so that he might regain his sight.
But Ananias answered, Lord, I have heard from many about this man, how much evil he has done to your saints at Jerusalem,
and that he has authority from the chief priests to bind all who call on your name.
But the Lord said to him, go, for he is a chosen instrument of mine to carry my name before the Gentiles and the kings and the children of Israel,
for I will show him how much he must suffer for my namesake.
So Ananias departed, and he entered the house, and laying hands on him, he said,
Brother Saul, the Lord Jesus who appeared to you on the road by which you came has sent me so that you may regain your sight and be filled with the Holy Spirit.
It's the part in the story where we see God using the participation, the obedience of others,
and the way in which he wants to interact with our lives.
He wants us to participate in his plan of taking people from going in their own way and redirecting them,
having them repent and go in the way that he has called them to.
He wants our participation in that.
God tells Ananias, I have a purpose for you, and that purpose is going to involve Saul's repentance.
And I think rightly so, Ananias has a few questions, right?
He's like, yeah, we've been praying that when that guy gets here that something will happen so that he can't kill us,
and now you're telling me that he's blind?
That sounds like an answered prayer to me.
God's like, yeah, I appreciate your prayers.
I heard them, and actually my plan is better than the plan that you think it is.
So you think I'm going to blind him and stop him from persecuting you,
but actually I'm going to get a hold of his attention.
I'm going to flip his life 180 degrees around.
I'm going to use you to extend my grace and my forgiveness to him.
He's going to understand the gospel, and he is going to go and preach the gospel to the kings
and to the Gentiles and to the house of Israel.
God's plan is so much better than our plan, and he's calling us to participate in it.
And it's okay if we have some questions, but at the end of the day, what he ultimately wants from us is our obedience.
Isn't this a beautiful picture of the kingdom of God?
He regularly uses our obedience to impact the lives of those around us.
And here's the thing.
God doesn't need Ananias' obedience.
Right?
Like God showed up at the road to Damascus, blinded him, and talked to him.
God's got all the tools he needs to make Saul turn around and walk in the opposite direction.
But he invites Ananias here, and I think it's beautiful.
It's so beautiful because God often is doing so much more than we could ever get our minds around.
Because by inviting Ananias to obedience, he's doing something both in Saul's life and Ananias' life.
By using Ananias, he was able to do a healing work in Saul's life,
and he was able to teach Ananias a very important lesson about the grace and forgiveness of God.
I'm trying to decide what I want to do here.
All right, we're just going to go fast, because I don't want to skip anything,
just in case the Lord wanted you to hear it.
So, I want to emphasize two points here.
The first is that God will intentionally use you to have an impact in the lives of those around you.
He will.
He has a plan to use your life to influence the lives of others.
Do you believe that?
And are you looking for opportunities?
Are you listening for opportunities for God to call you to obedience?
It's one of the things I love about how we do baptism here.
When we have people that sign up to do baptism,
the first question I ask them after we make sure they understand the gospel
and what they're signing up for is I say,
who's been spiritually influential in your life?
Would you want them to baptize you?
So, oftentimes the people that are doing the baptism
are the people that God has used in influencing these people towards Jesus.
It's a visible representation of how God works in the kingdom.
It's not the pastor that does all the spiritual work.
It's you.
It's me.
It's in our neighborhood.
It's in our workplace.
We are the ones doing the kingdom work.
God often uses us in the lives of others.
And what I would love, what I would love more than anything in our church
is I would love for it to become a competition
of who gets to baptize the most people, right?
I would love for us to get to a place
where we're looking for God to use us so much so that we're like,
man, next time there's a baptism, I need to be up there.
And look, at the end of the day, the work is on God.
Like, God has to do the work.
But man, if we would posture ourselves in a way
where we're constantly looking to be obedient
and used in the life of others,
how incredible would that be?
And how much more often would we have to fill this baptism tank?
So no matter what message you've heard from others in your life
or what you might think about yourself,
I want you to know you have a role to play in God's kingdom.
There are no bench players on Team Jesus.
Are you expecting to be used by Him?
Are you willing to be obedient to His invitation?
The second thing I want to point out here
is that the work God is...
All right.
The work that God is calling you to do
might include the very person that you least want to engage with
or extend grace to.
Let's not brush past the fact that Saul likely had a hand
in killing or imprisoning literal friends of Ananias.
And God is saying, Ananias, I want you to go
and I want you to place your hands on Him
so that He might be healed and receive the Holy Spirit.
And for the godliest people in the room,
we might say, like, yeah, we want our enemies to receive forgiveness.
But don't make me put my hands on them.
Right?
Don't make me touch that guy or that girl that did that thing to me.
This is the heart of the gospel,
that Jesus loved us and He gave His life for us
when we were His enemies.
And His call to those of us who have decided to turn from the wide road
that leads to destruction
and head the narrow road that leads to life,
His call for us is that we would love our enemies the way that He loved us.
So who is it in your life that you've written off?
Who is it that you think is too far gone?
Who is it that you assume will not listen to you?
Who might God be calling you to share the message of hope with or minister to?
Who might God be calling you to lay your hands on and heal through the power of forgiveness?
See, I know far too many Christians.
And I speak from a place of privilege because I've been wounded deeply,
but not to the level that some of you have been.
But at the end of the day, I see far too many Christians who hold on to bitterness
and unforgiveness towards others for far too long.
And not only are you keeping them from an opportunity to hear, to receive,
to experience the gospel of Jesus,
but you're holding on to bitterness that God does not want you to hold on to.
It's actually leading you to rot and decay in your soul.
So who might God be calling you to to go to lay your hands on to and say,
I forgive you because Jesus forgave me.
And I don't excuse what you did to me.
And I'm not going to put myself in a position where you can do it to me again,
but I forgive you.
I will skip this because we already talked about it a little bit.
But the reason we spent so much time on Saul's life and background last week
is for this point here.
Verse 16, 15.
Saul tells Ananias to go,
for he is a chosen instrument of mine to carry my name before the Gentiles
and the kings and the children of Israel.
See, God orchestrated Saul's life.
The experiences of Saul's life, where he was born, where he grew up,
the things that he knew about the Old Testament,
the things that he knew about Roman culture and philosophy,
God had orchestrated all of those things.
It made Saul the perfect candidate to be the apostle,
to the Gentiles, and to the rest of Israel.
He was the perfect person to bridge the gap between the nation of Israel and the Gentiles.
And I believe, ultimately, in some way, shape, or form, the same is true for you and me.
That God has created you on purpose and for a purpose.
Ephesians 2 says that you are his workmanship, created in Christ Jesus to do good works,
which he prepared in advance for you to do.
Not for me to do.
There are works for you to do, that I cannot do, that no one else in this room can do.
God has a purpose and a plan for you.
Do you believe that?
Do you believe that God knit you together in your mother's womb,
that he gave you your personalities, your skills, and your passions,
that he allowed you to have experiences that you had?
Even the bad experiences, that he allowed those experiences
so that you might have a ministry of reconciliation through your pain.
All so that you can play a unique role in the kingdom of God.
There are no second-class citizens in the kingdom of God.
All of us are needed at the table.
All right.
Last.
All of this crescendos to one thing.
Saul being baptized.
So Ananias departed.
He entered the house, laying his hands on him.
He said,
Brother, brother, Saul, can you imagine that moment?
Ananias, filled with anger and bitterness and frustration towards Saul
and the pain that he caused, his friends and family,
receiving enough, just enough, mustering up just enough grace of God
to say, you know what?
Welcome to the family.
I forgive you.
You imagine Saul, who had literally killed Christians up to this point,
being touched by a follower of the way and saying,
welcome to the family.
This is the transforming power of the gospel.
Brother Saul, the Lord Jesus, who appeared to you on the road by which you came,
has sent me so that you may regain your sight and be filled with the Holy Spirit.
And immediately something like scales froze from his eyes.
He regained his sight.
He arose and was baptized.
Again, the crescendo of this incredible story is Saul's baptism,
a symbol that he had received God's call on his life,
that he had stopped walking down the wide road that leads to destruction.
He had repented.
He had turned and he had started walking down the narrow road that ultimately leads to life.
And here's the thing.
This story would become a monument for the early church
and the church throughout human history,
that no one is too far gone for the grace of God.
I don't care where you've been, what you've done.
I don't care what you were doing last night.
There is no one who is too far gone for the grace of God.
Saul would later write to Timothy.
I love this.
Here is a trustworthy saying that deserves full acceptance.
Christ Jesus came into the world to save sinners, of whom I am the worst.
For that very reason, because I was the worst,
God has shown his patience as an example, as a monument for all those who would believe in him
and receive eternal life.
Saul is saying, look, God showed up so visibly, so intentionally in my life,
because I was a murderer.
I was literally killing his people.
He did that so that his people would realize there is no one too far gone for the grace of God.
I am an example that God's grace extends to anyone.
So maybe you're here, you've been running for a long time.
You've convinced yourself you're too far gone.
You've convinced yourself that your way is the right way
and that this way is ultimately going to lead to your satisfaction
and to your life.
I'm here to tell you that God has been placing signposts along the way
to tell you that there is a cliff up ahead
and that you will hit rock bottom eventually.
How will you respond?
Will you receive that confrontation?
Will you turn and will you repent?
Maybe you're here and you've submitted your life to him.
You've been repeatedly giving in to the same sin or temptation.
Let the story of Saul be a reminder to you that even in the midst of your continual brokenness,
continual disobedience, that there is continual grace.
But like we read in Romans 6,
that grace is not so that you can keep on sinning and sinning and sinning and sinning.
That grace is so that you can realize that your sin is going to lead you to death
and that you can walk in the opposite direction.
Here's my main point.
We're done.
I promise.
I worked really hard on this main point.
It rhymes, kind of.
So if you're taking notes, this is what I want you to remember from this whole morning.
That God is in the business of redirecting people from their way to the way.
And he often uses us as guides along the way.
God, he is in the business of redirecting people from their way to the way.
There are two spiritual directions.
We're all either going the wide road that leads to destruction
or the narrow road that leads to life.
And God is constantly, as a loving father,
trying to redirect people who are walking towards this cliff.
He's trying to invite them to life and to life more abundantly.
And here's what he does.
He uses us along the way.
Yes, he can shine down a light from heaven,
but far more often than not, he uses you and me in the lives of others.
So, if you're in here and you haven't yet decided to follow Jesus,
maybe today is the day.
Maybe there's been signposts along the way,
there's been conviction, and you're just like,
nah, I'm good, I'm going to keep doing my own thing.
My prayer today is that you would realize that you've been walking down a road
that ultimately will lead to your destruction,
and that God is a loving father who's inviting you to repent
and to turn and go the opposite direction,
not because he's a cosmic tyrant that demands obedience
because he's a loving father that wants you to experience life and life more abundantly.
Continue down this path, and it will lead to destruction,
but repent and follow his way, and it will lead to life.
Followers of Jesus, are you expecting God to use you to have an impact in the lives of others?
Do you view yourself as a guide along the path of others' lives?
And who might God be calling you to minister to or to bring hope and healing,
the hope and healing of the presence of Jesus?
Don't underestimate what God wants to do in your life.
All right, so we're going to end with baptism.
We try to make some space.
Our kids are going to come in here in just a second
because we want our kids to be in here and to see baptism
and to celebrate baptism with us
because it is the crescendo of the Christian life, right?
It is like this is the turning point of going your own way
and turning and repenting and going the way of Jesus.
Baptism is the perfect way to end this message
because it's exactly how Saul's story ends
and God's story through Saul begins.
This is baptism.
Saul's story ends
and God's story through Saul begins.
We're saying I have died to my old self
that was walking the wide road
and I have been born again, made new.
I'm a new person going a new direction.
And will you be perfect?
Absolutely not.
Will you find yourself again and again
feeling the pull of culture
and the pressure of your friends
to turn and go back the opposite direction?
Yes.
Will you have muscle memory?
Will you step out of your house from time to time
and start back down that wide road
and it take a while for you to realize like,
oh wait, we're not going that way anymore.
You ever moved?
You ever lived in a town
and moved from that like in the same town?
But like the path you go out of your house
is different from how you normally do?
Anybody else have that experience?
It's awful because like for three weeks
you get in your car
and you just go back towards your old house
and you're like, oh wait,
this isn't where I live anymore.
So that is often going to be your experience.
As you repent, as you turn to Jesus,
you will walk out of your house
and start going the opposite direction.
You will continue in patterns of sin,
but the Holy Spirit has power to give you victory.
Baptism is a picture that we've realized we're lost,
that we're walking our own way.
It's a visible symbol that we've repented
and we are willing to die to our own self
and submit our life to Jesus.
Baptism is done by guides along the way.
I love, again, we'll read Romans 6 one more time
as we're ending.
Welcome, children.
How are we?
Good.
I preached for a long time.
I'm so sorry.
All right.
Romans 6.
Don't you know that all of us
who were baptized into Christ
were baptized into his death.
We therefore buried with him
through baptism into death
in order that just as Jesus was raised from the dead
through the glory of the Father,
we may to live a new life.
Multiple people have pre-decided
that they're going to make that decision this morning
if you're in here
and you have not yet made that decision.
There are towels.
There are clothes.
We would love to celebrate this with you.
Please, as we sing,
consider whether or not
today might be the day
that God gets your attention
and that you turn from the wide road
that leads to destruction
back to the narrow road
that leads to life.
Let's pray.
Father, we are so thankful
for this morning
to celebrate these decisions.
We're so thankful,
God, that you love us enough
to confront us
in our own direction,
in our own way,
that you wake us up
from the death,
the sin that leads to death,
and you turn us around
to obedience that leads to life.
God, may we be a people
who are known
for the direction of our lives.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
All right.